Inventory of the Jean Graham Alinsky papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jean Graham Alinsky papers
1908-1984
92056
Alinsky, Jean Graham
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, correspondence, legal and financial papers, memoranda, press releases and printed matter, relating to the career of Saul Alinsky as a radical and organizer of impoverished communities in the United States. Includes published writings and a few papers of Saul Alinsky.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Eric Hoffer papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Fred Ross papers, Special Collections, Stanford University
Industrial Areas Foundation records, Special Collections, University of Illinois, Chicago
Saul David Alinsky collection, Trinity College Library
Biographical Note
1916 May 17 Born Jean La Verne Graham, New York
1938 B.A., Vassar College
1942 January Married Frederick Schick
1948 Divorced Frederick Schick
Circa 1951 Assistant, Museum of Modern Art, New York
1952 May 15 Married Saul Alinsky in Spartanburg, South Carolina
1956 Diagnosed with multiple sclerosis
Circa 1964 Moved to Carmel, CA
1967 Honorary Chair, Help the Children Committee
1969 Divorced Saul Alinsky
1999 Died, Monterey, CA
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers contain Jean Graham Alinsky's memoirs of her marriage to Saul Alinsky. Correspondence, legal papers, memoranda, reports, and printed matter relate to the career of Saul Alinsky as an organizer of impoverished communities in the United States. Organizational records from the Industrial Areas Foundation as well as a few personal papers of Saul Alinsky are also included.
In a 1983 letter, Jean Graham Alinsky wrote that she was "determined to write a biography" of her second husband Saul Alinsky (Box 1, Folder 28). The bulk of the Jean Graham Alinsky file consists of Jean's research materials for her Saul Alinsky biography, including extensive clippings, as well as her personal memoirs and biographical writings on Saul Alinsky (Box 2). These writings, compiled from 1980-1984, are in fragments with several sections and pages missing. Except for two letters received from Saul Alinsky, the correspondence file consists mainly of holiday cards, personal letters from unidentified friends, and a few pieces of legal correspondence.
The Saul Alinsky file contains a few writings of Saul Alinsky as well as some records from the Industrial Areas Foundation, a Chicago-based organization founded by Alinsky in 1940.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Jean Graham Alinsky file and Saul Alinsky file.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Radicalism--United States.; Community organization--United States.; Alinsky, Saul David, 1909-1972.
Collection Contents
- JEAN GRAHAM ALINSKY FILE, 1908-1984 (Box 1-5)
  Contains biographical materials, memoirs, essays, correspondence, and printed matter, mainly on the life and career of Saul Alinsky and her own battle with multiple sclerosis.
  Arranged by physical form.
  - Biographical file, 1916-1984
    - Birth certificate, 1916 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Vassar College diploma, 1938 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Frederick Schick divorce papers, 1948 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Jean Graham and Saul Alinsky marriage certificate, 1952 (Folder 1: 4)
      Certified copy from 1978
    - Kathryn and Lee David Alinsky adoption records, 1952 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Clippings, 1953-1954, 1965 (Folder 1: 6)
    - YMCA award certificate, 1966 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Saul Alinsky divorce papers, 1968-1969 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Vassar Class of 1938 questionnaire, circa 1972 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Conservatorship papers, 1972-1984 (Folder 1: 10)
      Includes copy of Saul Alinsky's death certificate
    - Photograph of Jean Graham Alinsky, 1980 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Address book and calendar, 1980s, undated (Folder 1: 12)
  - Correspondence, 1908-1910, 1971-1984
    Except for two letters from Saul Alinsky, consists of holiday cards and letters received from friends and a small amount of legal correspondence.
    - Undated (Folder 1: 13-14)
      Includes one letter from Saul Alinsky
    - 1908-1910 (Folder 1: 15)
    - 1960 (Folder 1: 16)
    - 1967 (Folder 1: 17)
    - 1971 (Folder 1: 18)
    - 1972 (Folder 1: 19)
    - 1973 (Folder 1: 20)
    - 1974 (Folder 1: 21)
    - 1975 (Folder 1: 22)
    - 1976 (Folder 1: 23)
    - 1978 (Folder 1: 24)
    - 1979 (Folder 1: 25)
    - 1980 (Folder 1: 26)
    - 1981 (Folder 1: 27)
    - 1982 (Folder 1: 28)
    - 1983 (Folder 1: 29)
    - 1984 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Writings, 1950s-1984
    - "Embezzlement as a Fine Art", 1950s (Folder 2: 1)
    - Notes, 1960s-1980 (Folder 2: 2-3)
    - Memoirs of marriage to Saul Alinsky, fragments, circa 1980-1984 (Folder 2: 4-14)
    - Untitled essay on New Paltz, New York, 1980 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Untitled essay on Rules for Radicals, 1981 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Subject file, 1944-1984
    - Alinsky, Saul, 1944-1984
      - Undated (Folder 2: 17)
      - 1944 (Folder 2: 18)
      - 1946 (Folder 2: 19)
      - 1961 (Folder 2: 20)
      - 1962 (Folder 2: 21)
      - 1963 (Folder 2: 22)
      - 1964 (Folder 3: 1-3)
      - 1965 (Folder 3: 4-6)
      - 1966 (Folder 3: 7-8)
      - 1967 (Folder 3: 9-10)
      - 1968 (Folder 3: 11-12)
      - 1969 (Folder 3: 13)
      - 1971 (Folder 3: 14)
      - 1972 (Folder 3: 15-16)
      - 1973 (Folder 3: 17)
      - 1974 (Folder 4: 1-2)
      - 1975 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1978 (Folder 4: 4)
      - 1979 (Folder 4: 5)
      - 1981 (Folder 4: 6)
      - 1983 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Anthropology, 1979-1980 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Archaeology, 1980-1984 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Architecture, 1960s-1980s (Folder 4: 10)
    - Brussell, Mae, 1972-1974, 1982-1984 (Folder 4: 11-12)
      Includes copies of Brussel's World Watchers International newsletter
    - Chicago (Ill.), 1962-1974 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Citizens Action Program, 1973 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Environmentalism, circa 1980 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Fort Ord (Calif.), 1969 (Folder 4: 16)
      Relates to mutiny trial
    - Judaism, 1967, 1980 (Folder 4: 17)
    - Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1980 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1979 (Folder 4: 19)
    - King, Martin Luther, 1961, 1982 (Folder 4: 20)
    - Ku Klux Klan, 1976-1980 (Folder 4: 21)
    - Multiple sclerosis, 1967-1983 (Folder 4: 22-23)
    - Plath, Sylvia, 1965 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Poetry, 1970s (Folder 5: 2)
    - Reagan, Ronald, 1984 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1960s-1984 (Folder 5: 4-8)
- SAUL ALINSKY FILE, 1946-1972 (Box 5-6)
  Contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, and printed matter.
  - Correspondence, 1952-1967 (Folder 5: 9)
    Includes two poems in honor of Alinsky
  - Organizations file, 1957-1969
    - Community Service Organization, 1960 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Industrial Areas Foundation, 1957-1969
      - Circulars, 1965-1969 (Folder 5: 11)
      - Letters received, 1961-1966 (Folder 5: 12)
      - Memoranda, 1957-1961
        - Nicholas von Hoffman to Saul Alinsky on the Grand Boulevard Project, 1957 (Folder 5: 13)
        - Saul Alinsky to Robert T. Dunn on the Chelsea Community Council, 1960 February 10 (Folder 5: 14)
        - Saul Alinsky on articles in Christian Century magazine, 1960 November 30 (Folder 5: 15)
        - Saul Alinsky on articles in The Chicago Sun Times, 1961 April 12 (Folder 5: 16)
        - Craig Heverly on meeting with Chicago Housing Committee, 1962 (Folder 5: 17)
      - Publications, 1960-1962 (Folder 5: 18)
        Includes Action to Equality of Opportunity
      - Reports, 1960-1966 (Folder 5: 19)
        Includes annual report from 1960 and position paper on the Episcopal Society for Cultural and Racial Unity
  - Speeches and writings, 1946-1972
    - Reveille for Radicals, University of Chicago Press, 1946 (Folder 5: 20)
      Copy inscribed by Saul to Jean
    - Notes and outlines, 1950s-1960s (Folder 6: 1-3)
    - Untitled essay on intellectuals, undated (Folder 6: 4)
    - Untitled essay on welfare workers, undated (Folder 6: 5)
    - "Idea Notes on the Day We Took Christmas", undated (Folder 6: 6)
    - "Note on the Democratic Process", undated (Folder 6: 7)
    - "On Public Housing and Urban Renewal", undated (Folder 6: 8)
    - "The Crime of Crime Prevention," address to the California Democratic Council Convention and Issues Conference, 1961 March 4. (Folder 6: 9)
    - "Citizen Participation and Community Organization in Planning and Urban Renewal," address to the Chicago chapter of the National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials, 1962 January 29 (Folder 6: 10)
    - "The War on Poverty: Political Pornography," The Journal of Social Issues, 1965 January (Folder 6: 11)
    - "Of Means and Ends," Union Seminary Quarterly Review, 1967 January (Folder 6: 12)
    - Rules for Radicals file, 1968-1972
      - "Note for Chapter on Self-Interest,", circa 1968 (Folder 6: 13)
      - "The Purpose," chapter draft, circa 1970 (Folder 6: 14)
      - Rules for Radicals, Vintage Books, 1972 (Folder 6: 15)
    - John L. Lewis: An Unauthorized Biography, Vintage Books, 1970 (Folder 6: 16)
    - The Professional Radical: Conversations with Saul Alinsky, Harper and Row, 1970 (Folder 6: 17)